3. Beers

Joe’s apartment was modern and functional. He enjoyed clear lines and muted colors mixed with carefully curated, minimalist Scandinavian furniture from the mid-20th century. Visitors often remarked that it resembled an Airbnb more than a home. However, Joe enjoyed its cleanliness and detachment, finding solace in its calming atmosphere. But not today. The events in Georgetown had left him deeply unsettled. Unwelcome memories flashed before his eyes, but he tried to shake them away.

He turned to social media, his usual favorite pastime, but the absurd theories and opinions about Georgetown only agitated him more. Unable to bear the online ramblings, he said, “Vesta, please suggest something entertaining.”

“Sure, Joe, based on your previous nights, how about I create an intriguing movie with breathtaking action scenes starring Bruce Willis, Tom Cruise, and the adorable Charlotte Hanson?”

“Thanks, but no thanks.” Joe rolled his eyes at the cheerful and exaggerated response that seemed to be typical for conversational AI since its beginnings. Having a movie generated for him based on his preferences was usually a guaranteed way to spend an entertaining evening, at least if you mixed some beers in. However, this “algotrash” wasn’t exactly what you would call a cinematic masterpiece. And things blowing up in 3D was the last thing he needed today.

“Vesta, connect me with David.”

“Hi Joe, what brings me the pleasure of seeing you?”

“Dave, I was wondering, you in for a beer tonight?”

“Sure thing; our usual watering hole, then?”

“Yep, see you in 30, ok?”

David Donnelly closed the connection with a smile and nod, grabbed his jacket, and headed out of his campus office.

David Donnelly was Joe’s mentor when he started teaching at MIT. Despite being ten years older than Joe, David became one of the few people that Joe considered a friend. As an engineering professor, David enjoyed building things with his hands. He had slightly longer grey hair, a full beard that was not always neatly trimmed, and broad shoulders from physical work. David broke the conventions of academic style, but he was one of the sharpest minds in his field.

Now he was sitting at their bar’s favorite table, scratched and dented by uncounted patrons over the years. The scent of hop and worn leather was hanging in the air. The room was lit by a mix of neon signs behind the bar and in the windows, large and simple lamps hanging from the ceiling, and the screens on the walls. Usually, these screens showed sports like the latest Patriots game, but not today. David averted his gaze from the videos and interviews discussing all kinds of theories about the incident in Georgetown, which had shaken up the nation. Just then, he glanced at the door and saw Joe entering the bar. He raised his hand to greet his friend.

Joe gratefully accepted the still-cold pint of Samuel Addams waiting for him at their table. “So, how did your day go, professor?” Joe asked after he had sat the glass back on the wooden table.

“Actually, it was pretty well going until, you know…” David said and waved his hand at the screens. “And I imagine yours wasn’t better?”

“If anything, it ruined my favorite lecture,” Joe answered, only half-jokingly.

David could feel the tension that lay beneath the answer.

“Probably felt harder than for most of your students. I know that it’s hard.”

“After all those years, someone would expect that it’s getting easier, and it does. Until it doesn’t.”

“Your parents were good people, Joe. Your dad helped me figure things out when I was just getting the hang of the whole academic circus.”

The memory of the burned-out car where his parents died over 30 years ago made Joe shiver, but he didn’t say anything.

David knew that Joe wasn’t one to talk about what he tried to keep inside, under the veneer of the intelligent, slightly arrogant, but always entertaining expert. He changed the subject: “I’m going to the cabin tomorrow, and guess what? I have a new hydro-generator already on the truck bed, so there will be enough power for comfort even if I have some spoilt visitors from the big city.”

That made Joe chuckle. “You’re getting old and lazy. That’s the real reason, Dave!”

David smiled. His cabin in the woods was where he spent most of his free time, away from Boston, screens, and media.

“Why, you should come and visit me. There’s always something to do I could use a hand with.”

“The last time I visited, it was totally disconnected from the world, and I’m not the offline type.”

“Ain’t that the truth? But this won’t change anytime soon. Sitting in a valley surrounded by a magnificent forest does that for you. That’s exactly why I chose it: going off the grid and drinking my morning coffee with nothing to view but the sun rising over the lake.”

“To your little Walden, Dave!”

The air was laced with the bittersweet tang of old beer and the low rumble of conversations, punctuated by the clink of their glasses.

“I wonder what Jason is up to now,” asked David.

“Nothing short of world domination for Bolt and his AI chips,” snorted Joe, taking a deep gulp from his glass. His former research assistant turned tech billionaire was a bit of a sore spot for Joe.

“Have you read Emily’s piece about the new research facility he’s set up? I find the idea of self-organizing AI intriguing. And that’s a lot of money going into the region.”

“You sound like a politician, Dave.”

“Seems like politicians are still throwing a lot of cash at anyone who produces AI chips in the U.S. I mean, it’s a smart move, right? I thought you’d be all in since it makes your research even more relevant.”

“If that’s even possible,” Joe laughed, now clearly feeling the slight buzz of his beers. “But really, Bolt is the last one who needs public funding. The guy is backed by venture capital that seems to be endless and has so many personal funds that he’s buying every promising startup he comes across. It’s not good to allow one guy to build a de facto monopoly that depends on his personal whims.”

“Look who is now sounding like a politician,” David chuckled.

“No, really, I know this guy. He’s seriously deranged.”

“Well, that’s why you kicked him off your team, alright. But it seems it served him well.”

“Whatever,” Joe grumbled, his face clearly showing signs of disgust.

David was absentmindedly rotating the half-full glass in his hand. “Emily made it quite clear that the person in question is not the digital savior he believes he is. It’s nice to hear a genuine human voice amidst all the AI pseudo-journalism masquerading as news these days.” He looked up to Joe, “Have you spoken to her ever since?”

“No, no, I haven’t. I’m sure that she’s not too keen on that either.”

“It’s a shame. She was the only woman who showed promise to handle you.” David smiled sadly and silently added, “And that was exactly why you ruined it.”

8. Suspect

Alex Mercer placed his trainers neatly in the locker. When he got the message, he had just returned from an extended run through Rock Creek Park. There would be another briefing on the killing cars, and personal presence was required. It wasn’t unusual for those briefings to be in person only due to the various security considerations in high-stakes cases like this one. After a quick shower, he got dressed and locked the locker with his badge, which had an NFC chip. The badge also worked as a key using Near Field Communication, giving the holder extra access rights and adding another layer of security to biometric locks. Looking forward to the new developments, he made his way to the conference room just before the briefing started.

“Here we go again,” Jake greeted his partner with another cup of coffee. “I hope you had no other plans for tonight,” Mercer said as he took the cup from his friend. He knew that Jake’s wife, April, and their two kids had planned to go out for dinner with him.

“Well, aren’t we always on duty? But still, I hope it’s worth it.”

“At least it looks like we are going to be spared another lecture by Hartman,” Mercer noticed as the brass entered the room, this time without civilian backup.

“You two had a thing going on, haven’t you? It was a bit hard to ignore, Alex. There was some chemistry between you, alright,” Jake joked. He knew the moment the professor walked up to the lantern a few hours ago that this was the type to annoy Mercer. His partner was the ground-to-earth type who valued men and women who owned a problem when they saw one. Hartman seemed far from it on all accounts.

“Listen up, everyone. We’ve got a major update,” Assistant Director Helen Koop declared to the packed room. “I know there’s been skepticism about our new AI, but SENTINEL delivered—in an unexpected way, I must add. However, this proves that analyzing the data was definitely the right call.”

The large display changed to show an image of Joe Hartman. “Not him again,” Mercer mumbled, and Jake rolled his eyes.

Koop stopped and cleared her throat to silence the murmuring in the room. Hartman clearly left a strong impact on the agents, although it wasn’t the most positive one.

“The man was standing right next to us, and no one had any clue. However, we can’t ignore SENTINEL’s analysis. Our main suspect for the Washington attack is Joseph Hartman.” And with this, the room full of seasoned professionals erupted into chaos.

Helen Koop watched the discussions and gave them some time. She saw the agents’ emotions range from disbelief and shock to acceptance. That was her own journey as well. Her initial reaction was plain disbelief. However, after reading the assessment, she found that it well aligned with her uneasy feeling after her last exchange with Hartman. Nevertheless, it still left many questions open to her, but she didn’t show them. There would be a time to answer them.

“Well, your instincts about Hartman were obviously right,” Jake said, still processing the information.

“My instincts were telling me Hartman was a jerk, not a cold-blooded killer. I call bullshit, and I can’t believe you think otherwise. There’s something wrong with that guy, no question. But that doesn’t fit. No way.”

“We don’t know about motive yet, we don’t know how SENTINEL figured it out, it could have been an accident, negligence, whatever.”

“Exactly, and now the whole machinery is set into motion, based on what exactly?” Mercer was shaking his head in disbelief. What about due process and evidence standards?

The meeting adjourned, and Mercer exchanged a look with Jake. They both knew how serious the situation was, but they also had a lot of questions. The agents filed out, but Mercer and Lin were among those asked to stay behind. Maybe now they would get some answers.

The agent in charge, Tom Edwards, resumed the briefing but focused solely on Hartman’s planned arrest.

“Guys, I know you have questions, but details about how the attack was carried out are on a need-to-know basis right now.”

Mercer, who did his share of special operations as a ranger, understood operational security very well. But this was the FBI, and he expected more than a number an algorithm had spit out for an arrest.

“So now we’re talking about an attack,” Jake whispered in Mercer’s ear, who was slowly shaking his head.

“What we know is that Hartman returned to Boston an hour ago. The Boston Field Office is preparing to go after him as soon as possible, but we also want to be on site. Mercer, Lin, you meet with me on the helipad in 10. Gear up.”

The first agents got moving and Alex stepped over to Edwards.

“Tom, what’s this? We are going out because Koop’s chatbot told us so without proper investigation or recon. We’re now some glorified errand boys with a badge doing what a computer tells us, or what?”

“Stop whining, Mercer, and saddle up,” Edwards said as he checked on his watch.

Thirty minutes later, they were on the way to Boston in a silent, matte black electric chopper, watching the city lights flicker below in the clear, chilly night.

Wordlessly, Edwards handed Mercer a tablet with a summary of SENTINEL’s report. The brief covered several points that checked all the boxes: Hartman’s expertise in AI and his involvement in the development of the traffic network, indicators of a narcissistic personality disorder, and various biometrical and behavioral indicators observed during the briefing a few hours ago. Analysis of footage from in-room cameras had revealed strong emotions that Hartman had attempted to conceal, with his breathing and heart rate showing patterns of evasion, anger, and guilt. Mercer silently handed the tablet back to Edwards with a nod, grateful that Tom had given him a glimpse of what was going on. The report sounded conclusive on its own; Mercer had to admit that. However, despite not being a friend of the professor, this still didn’t sit right with him.

But one thing was clear now. He understood well why the brass was so reluctant to reveal the details. The fact that the FBI was also capturing footage and analyzing the participants of internal meetings was news, and not in a good way. He wondered what SENTINEL’s watchful eyes might have revealed about him. And what it meant for the bureau. Integrity was always part of what the letters FBI stood for, but now it seemed that trust was replaced by technology, which bothered him even more than Hartman’s role in the case.

15. Sarah

Richard Clayton sat in his Pentagon office with a red coffee mug in his hand, originally embellished with the golden Marine Corps crest, the kind you can get in a souvenir shop. The crest had faded over the years, and the mug had seen many stations of Clayton’s career, but it had been a gift when he had completed basic training, and it held sentimental value for him. There were not many things left of the little time he had with his wife Nancy, who passed away too early and left him as a single parent.

Clayton was intently listening to the report he received from Luke Brennan, standing at the parade rest before him, in stark contrast to his casual attire.

“It was the right call to abort the mission and allow Hartman to escape, Captain. This gives us more operational freedom than having him sit in an FBI interview room or a cell for that matter. But not much. Obviously, the doctor is more resourceful than I initially gave him credit for. He’s still at large. But then again, maybe it’s just the FBI being really bad at their job. Cutting down on staff and relying on computers instead might not have been the smartest move for law enforcement, after all.”

“Actually, sir, it's not that simple,” Brennan said, his eyes suggesting there was more to come.

“Go ahead, Brennan, I’m listening.”

“One of the Agents, General, he’s one of ours. Well, sort of.”

“Come again?”

“Major Mercer was the agent who took the initiative after we started the diversion.”

“Mercer? He wasn’t bad for a grunt. It’s a shame that he left the Rangers,” said Clayton, whose task force included elements of the Army Rangers. He remembered Alexander Mercer well as a very capable officer who had had the potential to go far in his military career but resigned under circumstances not entirely clear to the General after he had been reassigned to another unit.

After a moment of thought, Clayton continued: “That may give us a different angle on the matter, Captain. Depending on your progress in the next 24 hours, we might need to bring him into the fold. The clock is ticking, Luke. Once the autonomous drone program is deployed, the U.S. military will be changed forever, and there will be no turning back. Find Hartman, Captain. Dismissed!”

Brennan snapped to attention and saluted sharply before he turned around and left the room.

As Richard Clayton closed his eyes, he couldn't help but think about the young, blonde Marine lieutenant from the photograph on his desk in his quarters. He picked up the photograph, his fingers tracing the edges of the frame.

Twelve months ago, thousands of miles away

Lieutenant Sarah Clayton was cautiously moving through the ruins of the small village, her M4 Carbine at the low ready, her finger resting on the rifle’s frame.

She heard the voice of her squad’s Sergeant Andrew Miller next to her: “I feel like someone is watching us, LT.”

“Copy that, Sarge,” Sarah answered without taking her eyes off the scenery washed over by the pale morning light, her head on a swivel. Miller was a seasoned Marine, and like any butter bar with their commission, she was very much listening to what her senior non-commissioned officer told her.

Their reconnaissance mission was based on intelligence indicating that insurgents were holding Private Wilson, who was missing in action, captive at this location. The young Marine’s prospects were grim, assuming he was still alive. Her headset crackled, and she signaled her Marines to stop.

“Hammer actual, Eagle Eye, over”

“Go ahead, Eagle Eye, over”

“Hammer, be advised that an Erebos drone is deployed in your area. Confirm your IFF transponders are operational, over.” Clayton and her team had been briefed on the new experimental autonomous MQ-50X Erebos drone when they received their kit’s upgraded IFF, short for Identify Friend or Foe, transponders.

Clayton switched to the squad’s tactical network. “Everybody, transponder check.”

Sarah checked the transponder on her own harness after all marines had called in with a green status.

“Eagle Eye, Hammer actual. All transponders green.”

“Roger that, Hammer. Eagle Eye, out”

Clayton signaled the team to move on. Their Danner Mojave boots were kicking up dust, getting carried away by the wind and forming small clouds.

“What was command thinking sending one of those sketchy birds into our AO?” Lance Corporal Jarred Lowry, who had taken point, asked over the tactical network.

“It won’t drop on your head, Lowry, and even if it did, there’s not much to damage. Now cut the chatter!” Clayton reprimanded the corporal under the soft chuckles of her team.

“I wouldn’t count it out, LT,” said Miller quietly, raising his head and looking at the sky. “If the techs at the base are to believed, those things are far from ready for battle.”

Their point man, Lowry, raised his fist at a hill, signaling the squad to stop. He turned to Clayton, pointed his index and middle finger to his eyes, and then down the hill. Sarah crawled slowly to Lowry’s position and looked through her field glasses. Now, she saw the entry of a cave partly obscured by a camouflage net. Fifty meters left to it were a number of wooden panels on the ground, covered with rocks and sand. Looking to the right, she counted three figures in fatigues sitting under a ledge and smoking with AK-47 Kalashnikovs in their laps.

After moving back from the top of the hill, she briefly conferred with Miller and then spoke softly over the tactical network: ”Enemy position one hundred meters ahead below the hill. At least three armed opposition visible to the right, unknown oppo in a cave structure. Fifty meters left of the cave a covered ground hole.”

Lowry and Solano, you take out the three guys from the hill and provide cover. We move to the cave and clear it out, but be aware that our man might be in there as well. Try not to shoot or frag Wilson. Await my go. Are we clear?”

After receiving the all-clear from her squad, Sarah called in the enemy position with Eagle Eye and requested air support.

Then she again spoke over the tactical network: “The cavalry is on the way. Let’s smoke those bastards and get Wilson out there. Go, go, go!”

Corporals Lowry and Solano aimed at the three men, who were still smoking and never saw their deaths coming, their heads exploding into clouds of pink mist. The rest of the team was already carefully moving down the slope to the cave, taking cover when possible. Alarmed by the shooting, more armed men came running out of the cave, already emptying their automatic weapons in the Marines’ direction. Bullets tore into the rocks next to Sarah, who drove to the ground and took aim at the enemy with her carbine. She’s always been a great shot and didn’t miss this time, either. Not all of her men were so lucky. Private Alejandro Estevez, a young Marine on his first deployment, was squarely hit and didn’t move after he went down.

The firefight lasted only minutes. After every enemy was either dead or dying and their weapons secured, Sergeant Miller took two men and checked out the cave. They found nothing apart from leftover rations and crates of ammo. Sarah looked around the carnage, and her eyes rested on the wooden panels.

Lowry, who had moved with Solano to Estevez, called Sarah: “LT, Lowry. The good news is that Estevez still breaths.”

“Copy that, Lowry. Move him down to cover until our ride home arrives. They are 10 mikes out.” Ten minutes could be an eternity with a bullet in your guts, but there was no way to speed things up, Sarah knew.

She tapped Miller on the shoulder, who was scanning the area for new threats.

“Sarge, let’s take a look at those planks. Maybe it’s just their latrine, but I wanna make sure.”

After carefully dragging away the panels in case it was rigged with explosives, Sarah looked down into the hole while Miller trained his M4 to the opening. They had finally found Private Wilson. Dirty, emaciated, and dehydrated, but alive.

“We will get you home, Marine,” Sarah said softly, as tears rolled down the young man’s face.

Miller, who was again on the lookout, thought he saw something like a reflection. Sarah Clayton noticed him focusing on a point on the horizon.

“You spotted something? Movement on the ground?”

“No, ma’am, in the air. Might be our ride,” the Sergeant answered thoughtfully.

“But that’s not the right direction. I will confirm with Eagle.”

“Wait one, that’s no gunship. It’s a drone,” he said as he looked through the optics of his binoculars.

“We could have used that 10 mikes ago,” Sarah said, slowly shaking her head.

The drone started to hover over their heads.

“That doesn’t look right, Sarge. Aren’t they supposed to be up much higher? What the fuck is it doing?”

Miller, who had his binoculars still trained on the drone, was the only one to see the bright shine of the ignition of the Hellfire missiles.

“Cover!” was the last thing Sarah Clayton heard before, in a blazing flash of light, the young Lieutenant and everyone around her were torn apart in a firestorm. The rest was only darkness and silence.

Long after the dust had settled, a small, 2-inch metallic device was found 75 meters up the hill. Its green LED ring was softly glowing, indicating that Sarah’s transponder was still functional.

As a soldier, Richard Clayton accepted death as a part of life. And blue-on-blue incidents did happen, killing and maiming with friendly fire. But those deaths were always human decisions. The decision to pull the trigger. The order to execute an operation. As flawed as human judgment was, there was always somebody responsible. Questions of humanity, morality, and justice had to be answered.

Until AI came and took over the killing.

Clayton’s eyes started to burn with grief and rage. As much as Sarah’s senseless death did hurt him more than words could say, the stakes were of a fundamental nature. This was his mission as a father and no less as an officer in the Armed Forces of the United States. He had to win this battle, so Sarah’s loss would at least help save other’s lives from the machines.

So help him, God.

17. Welcome to the Woods

“Jesus, David, put the gun down! It’s me, Joe!” Hartman yelped, holding his free hand up in the air.

“For fuck’s sake, Joe!” David Donnelly lowered the shotgun. Out of seemingly nowhere, Joe had that feeling of deja vu.

“For crying out loud, what are you doing in my pickup?! And if you don’t mind me saying, why do you look like utter shit?” David said while he helped Joe out of his precarious situation, being still partly tied to the straps on the truck’s bed.

“I wish I had been in your pickup, not on it,” Joe said as he eased himself onto the ground.

David stood before him in his plaid flannel shirt, looking like a lumberjack, and eyed him warily. “Well, whatever is behind this, don’t tell me it’s another scorned woman.”

“Hell has no fury… I wished it was as simple as this, Dave.”

David arched his left eyebrow and waited for Joe to continue.

“The FBI tried to arrest me for murder, while three thugs simultaneously tried to snatch me. Grenades were flying, but I somehow managed to bail and ended up here. Also, there was a woman, but it was Emily, and that was like the only good part of this crappy day.”

David let out a deep, good-natured laugh and helped Joe to his feet, shaking his head in disbelief.

“Sounds like a bat-shit crazy story… But are you sure you didn’t get a concussion or two from riding in my truck bed? Anyways, let’s clean you up, and then we can figure things out, okay?”

„Well, that’s some awkward shit,“ David summarized the situation dryly after Joe had told him about the events today. They sat at the dark wooden table next to the kitchenette, a cup of dark coffee in each man’s hand. The steel fronts of the freezer and oven stood out from the rest of the cabin’s warm, honey-toned color, which looked like it was completely constructed of pine wood. The rustic aesthetic and cozy setting starkly contrasted the thoughts that whirled through Joe’s mind.

“You’ve got to believe me, Dave. I haven’t done anything wrong, anything at all.”

David looked at his friend, who was now sporting one of his spare flannel shirts and had a white band-aid sticking to his forehead.

“Sure I do. You might be a dick at times, but you’re no killer. The question, however, is not what I think. The question is what the FBI thinks, and no less, what the three attackers—or the people behind them—do. But it stands to reason that both are related.”

“True enough,” Joe said as he looked into his coffee. “And why did SENTINEL conclude that I did it.”

“Well, that’s your area of expertise. Sorry to quote you here, but it’s all in the data, right?”

“About that,” Joe said as he rummaged in his daypack and produced the slim silver memory pack, “data is actually all I have.”

David nodded and stood up. He walked over to a cabinet and returned with a gun-metal grey laptop.

“Wow, you finally got internet in the woods?” Joe asked excitedly.

“No, buddy, ain’t possible here. The valley and the trees block everything over the air. That’s why I built my cabin here in the first place, you remember? And no cables are going down here, either. Produce my own power, pump my own water.

“Sure, I could set up some StarConnect stuff on the roof, but honestly, why would I want to do that?”

Joe could understand David’s logic but was frustrated nonetheless. “It would have been nice, for, you know, analyzing the damn data…?!”

“Joe, is using another remote AI wise? I mean, at least one artificial intelligence brought you into this situation. And I’m sure you believe you can set everything up securely, but what if you’re still traced back? Do you want to risk advertising your location to the FBI or your bearded friends with the grenades?”

After some reflection, Joe conceded that David had made a point. So, he would have to wrangle the data himself, using the tools Dave had available on his computer and coding the necessary scripts himself, even if his Python was a bit rusty. Some time ago, he had been actually writing code himself, not having it generated by yet another AI. He had to get back to basics, he supposed.

After helping David carry supplies from the truck into the cabin and unload the hydro-generator, he settled on the dark cushion of the wooden mission-style sofa, which stood next to the glass doors leading to the porch. He opened the computer, plugged in the memory pack, and sighed.

He would start with exploratory data analysis to better understand the dataset, plotting graphs and distributions to uncover any immediate patterns or outliers. In the end, it boiled down to sifting through the noise to find the signal hidden in the vast amounts of data.

David grabbed his truck’s keys from the kitchen table. “I’m going back to Boston and try to get more background information. I’ll also link up with Emily. You’re not alone with this, Joe.”

After a moment, he returned with his Remington 870 and walked over to Joe, whose eyes went wide with recognition at the sight of the shotgun.

“You know how to handle this?”

“Uhm, no, not really. Not a usual sight in Boston.”

“Yeah, but we’re in Maine, buddy, and it’s a staple around here,” said David, holding the gun sideways so Joe could take a better look.

“Here’s the safety,” he pointed to a button at the rear of the trigger guard. “Push it right to fire, left to safe. Remember, ‘Red, you’re dead.’

“Hold it firmly to your shoulder. It kicks like a mule. Pump the fore-end back and forth to chamber the next round.”

Joe took the shotgun with a mix of respect and fascination, toggled the safety for testing, and laid it on the coffee table.

“Do you really think I need this, Dave?”

“Better safe than sorry. But don’t point it at the FBI. That’ll end badly.”

After both men said their goodbyes, Joe made another cup of strong coffee. Just as he started to go through the data structure on the memory pack, he heard a noise outside the cabin.

“Shit,” he muttered to himself and grabbed the gun that was still resting on the coffee table. He made his way quickly to the door, avoiding the large windows.

He waited for a minute, but there was only silence. Cautiously, he opened the door and peered outside. Nothing.

He slowly stepped out the door, pressing the shotgun to his shoulder as David had shown him.

There it was again, the noise, like breaking twigs. A deer bull was looking back at him as startled as Joe himself and quickly vanished into the woods.

Joe took a deep breath of the chilly air. It smelled of pine and earth.

Not for the first time this day, Joe asked himself, “What have I gotten myself into?”

18. Addressing the Nation

Emily Stone was watching the live feed from the White House on her tablet. The app showed a little white checkmark in a blue circle with a red outline, indicating that this was real imagery by the U.S. government, not generated or altered by AI or other technology. For what it’s worth, the checkmark was protected by federal law, and using it unauthorized was a felony.

She saw President Robert Weston looking into the cameras sternly, sitting behind his desk in the Oval Office.

“My fellow Americans, today I speak to you in the aftermath of a harrowing event that unfolded 48 hours ago on the bustling streets of Georgetown—an event that has tested not only our resolve but also our faith in the technology that shapes our future. Autonomous vehicles, symbols of progress and innovation, were turned against us in a deliberate and heinous act of terror. This was not a failure of technology but a calculated assault on our way of life by individuals who wish to see us falter.”

Emily tensed. She knew that this framing would rally the media and public, with potentially dire consequences for Joe.

“First and foremost, I want to assure the nation that our law enforcement agencies are working tirelessly to bring those responsible to justice. The swift and decisive action taken by our police forces undoubtedly saved countless lives. This act of bravery, while effective, also serves as a stark reminder of the dangers we face in an interconnected world.”

Emily shook her head. One officer did the right thing, throwing the EMP grenade, and she was grateful for that. However, at its core, SENTINEL’s allegations against Joe demonstrated the reliance on artificial intelligence even in investigations dealing with malfunctioning AI. What a crazy irony.

“We have classified this devastating event as a terrorist attack. It is crucial to understand that the technology itself is not to blame; it was misused and manipulated by individuals with malicious intent. The AI that powers our daily lives—from the way we communicate to how we work and the methods by which we travel—is built on a foundation of trust and security. Our administration has been at the forefront of advancing these technologies, investing heavily in the AI chip industry to ensure that America remains a beacon of innovation on the global stage.

“Let me be clear: AI can and should be trusted. The actions of a few will not deter us from our path forward. We will continue to subsidize and support the AI industry, doubling down on our commitment to making America the leading AI nation in the world. Our dedication to this cause is unwavering, and we will take every necessary step to ensure the safety and security of our technology infrastructure.”

Taking a sip of her now lukewarm coffee, Emily noticed that the President’s speech was directed not only at the American people but also at investors and the stock markets, perhaps even more so at the latter.

“To the American people, I ask for your trust and vigilance. Trust in the measures we take to secure our nation and the technologies that will propel us into a future of unparalleled potential. And be vigilant, for the strength of our nation lies not only in our technological advancements but in the resilience and unity of its people.”

Her tablet chimed, and a notification popped up. Her editor, Julia Sanchez, asked if she watched Weston’s speech. Of course, she did. Her jaw clenched at the thought of facing her again soon.

“In the coming days, we will convene with industry leaders, technology experts, and law enforcement agencies to review our security protocols and ensure such an attack can never happen again. We will emerge from this stronger and more united, with a renewed commitment to a future where technology serves as a force for good.”

Weston leaned closer to the camera to emphasize his message.

“To those who seek to harm us, let this be a message: America will not be intimidated. We will defend our values, our way of life, and the technologies that have made us great. Together, we will overcome this challenge, as we have overcome so many before, and continue to lead the world into a new era of prosperity and peace.

“Thank you, God bless you, and God bless the United States of America.”

And with that, POTUS was replaced with the presidential seal on the feed’s window. To Emily, it seemed Weston didn’t say anything apart from the usual buzzwords required of a situation like this; it may well be enough to calm the American souls. Most people don’t care what technology does behind the scenes. It should just work, and they should be left alone with the details. AI had become so interwoven into the lives of the industrialized nations of the globe that it was more a commodity than anything else. Although this thought made Emily uncomfortable, this was the reality outside academic or certain political circles. Even the speech sounded conspicuously like it was AI-generated.

On the one hand, she was relieved that it didn’t mention Joe as the suspect, but the tone it had set worried her all the same: “Terrorist attack.” That didn’t bode well for Joe Hartman.

20. Interview

David Donnelly had some time to think while driving back to his home in Somerville. It wasn’t beyond Joe to have unwittingly played some part in this, but he was sure Hartman did not kill anyone. On the contrary, Joe was a good man who wanted to make the world a better place. Yes, he had his quirks, but that was only human.

However, the FBI believed otherwise. Some data points had to let SENTINEL conclude that Joe was behind the attacks. But how? That was probably a question for another day. As an engineer, he was trained to think in categories of cause and effect, action and reaction. He found it hard to accept the apparent fuzziness inherent to AI’s reasoning.

So he concentrated on the big questions: What caused the autonomous cars to wreak havoc and kill people, and why? Who were the mysterious men who tried to kidnap his friend? It stood to reason that both were related, so finding one answer could lead to the other. David wasn’t prone to conspiracy theories but was willing to make an exception in this case.

Even more when he spotted the two men in dark suits waiting in an unmarked car as he turned into his driveway.

“Dr. David Donnelly?” David turned around and measured the two suits approaching him after he had left his truck.

“Who wants to know?” David asked. He pulled his keyring out of his pocket and inconspicuously formed a fist with the keys barely protruding between his fingers. Surely, it wasn’t the best weapon for self-defense, but it added a sharp edge to his punch if needed.

“The FBI, sir. I’m Special Agent Alexander Mercer, and this is Special Agent Jake Lin,” Mercer said while both showed their badges. “May we ask you a few questions about Joe Hartman?”

David relaxed subtly, nodded, and unlocked the front door. This might be a chance to get useful information after all. “Come in, Agents.”

The countertop in David’s kitchen extended into a breakfast bar with seating for four. The pendant lights above them were reflected in the three large black coffees standing before the three men. Usually, David was sitting there alone, drinking his coffee - unless the table was covered with beers and cards when he and his friends played Texas Hold'em on long nights.

“So, have you been waiting long for me, gentlemen?” David asked Alex Mercer, who was sitting opposite of him.

“Well, Dr. Donnelly, you know, traffic cams. Your arrival was a bit advertised. Speaking of which, how was your trip to Maine?” Mercer responded with a question of his own. David filed that away for later, hoping his stowaway hadn’t been noticed.

“Uneventful, Agent Mercer,” David said and smiled, “but I believe you’re here because you wanted to ask about Joe Hartman. Why are you interested in my old friend?”

“Dr. Hartman is part of an ongoing investigation, and we want to learn a few things about his past. How many years have you known him?” Jake answered.

“For thirty years, give or take. I was his father’s research assistant, and later, I mentored him when he started as a lecturer at MIT. We’re colleagues and friends, but you know this already, I suppose.”

“Sorry to be so blunt, but are you aware of any childhood trauma that Joe had to deal with?” Mercer asked.

“I’m aware that he had a hard time when his parents died in a horrible car crash. Imagine being in school, and suddenly, the director comes to your class and brings you such a message. But shouldn’t you have this on file? There was a police investigation into this, but there was no evidence of foul play as far as I remember.”

“Yes, we are aware of this, Dr. Donnelly. But how did Joe cope with this loss? Wasn’t he furious?” Jake asked.

“He was devastated! But it became a strong motivator for him to build the technology to avoid such loss and pain.” David’s emotions were now clearly visible on his face.

Mercer and Lin exchanged a look.

“But tell me, Agents, where are you going with this line of questioning?” David asked, his voice firm again.

“Nowhere particular, Mr. Donnelly. Can you tell us a bit about his relationship with Jason Bolt?” Mercer asked.

“You know what they say about Bolt being some kind of wunderkind? That’s what he was—a brilliant mind and a gifted developer. Joe saw his potential and mentored him.”

“But then came a fall-out?”

“Yes, there has been talk about unethical behavior on Bolt’s part, and Joe ended his contract as a research assistant on his team. Joe was greatly disappointed, to say the least.”

“And what kind of unethical behavior are we talking about?” Jake asked.

“I’m actually not sure because Joe never told me so much. You will have to ask him yourself, I’m afraid.”

“Well, we will do, Dr. Donnelly,” Mercer said and stood up. “By the way, you don’t happen to know of the whereabouts of Joe Hartman, do you?”

“Why should I?” David asked back.

“I expected as much, Dr. Donnelly. Thanks for the coffee and your time. If you get new information about Dr. Hartman, here’s my card. We will be in touch,” Alex said as he and Jake walked out.

“And I expected that much,” David said softly as he closed the door behind them. He rubbed his face with his left hand. Playing poker helped, but this was a high-stakes game. “I’m too old for that shit, Joe,” he said, his eyes still closed.

Sitting in their car again, Jake shook his head. “I’m not quite sure who was interviewing whom here.”

“Yep, Donnelly was trying to gather information, and that was a message in itself. We can safely add him as a potential associate to the roster,” Mercer said while looking at the professor’s truck, which was still standing in the driveway.

“You think he’s had his hands in the killer cars?”

“Not really, but Donnelly comes across as a man of action. And those hillbilly vibes? If somebody told me he was part of a terrorist Luddite cell, you know, those anti-technology extremists, I would be inclined to believe this. Now I feel even less convinced that Hartman is the killer.”

“But still, right now, we need Hartman. Remember Koop wanting our badges? I’d like to keep mine,” Jake said, raising his brows.

“Fair enough. But Jake,” Mercer looked his friend in the eyes, “our job is to catch the bad guys. So let’s keep our eyes and minds open, okay?”

28. Identification

Emily Stone’s voice was curt. “Can we meet at the Great Dome?”

“Hello, Ms. Stone. Good to hear from you so soon. We’re not far. How about five minutes?” Alex Mercer replied smoothly.

“Alone, Agent Mercer. Can you do that?”

He glanced at his partner, Jake Lin, who shrugged.

“Yes, if it helps. But I assure you, Agent Lin is as trustworthy as I am,” Alex said with a smile.

“It’s not Agent Lin that I’m bothered about. What I have to ask is for your ears only. Does this work for you?”

“Sure, Ms. Stone. See you in a few at the steps of the Great Dome.”

After the call ended, Jake shook his head. “If I didn’t know better, I’d think she’s asking you out for dinner.”

“Pretty women do that all the time, Jake.”

“Hard to believe, buddy. But honestly, is that a wise move?”

“Do you think it’s a trap? I can handle it.”

“It’s more that we’re chasing too many loose ends. Getting Hartman should’ve been easy, but he vanished. Finding him should be a piece of cake,” Jake gestured at the traffic camera.

Mercer answered soberly, “This case isn’t what it seems. Sometimes, you must pull at different ends to unravel a complex situation.”

Five minutes later, Emily and Alex stood before the Great Dome.

“Here I am, Ms. Stone. Shall we walk?” Mercer asked, looking over the green lawn of Killian Court, buzzing with students.

“Thank you, Agent Mercer,” Emily said, her eyes scanning the court.

“Why are you sending those goons after me and David? Intimidation won’t work,” she added, her voice tense.

“I don’t know what you’re talking about,” he replied, meeting her gaze.

Emily pulled out her phone. “Let me show you,” she said, opening her camera roll. Distant laughter drifted over the lawn, which smelled of freshly cut grass.

She watched him closely. Recognition flickered in his eyes.

“You know who those men are, Mr. Mercer, right?”

Alex studied her determined face. Sharing information could help her open up. Time was ticking to get Hartman, and Emily might be their only lead.

“Yes. They’re not FBI. That’s Captain Luke Brennan,” he said, zooming in on Brennan’s face.

“They’re special operators. Marines. I served with Brennan under General Clayton. He’s capable but not discreet.”

Emily’s eyes widened. She scribbled the names in her notebook. “Why is the military involved? Is that legal?”

“Good question, Ms. Stone. I have no idea. But they’re dangerous men.”

“Did they try to kidnap Joe?”

Mercer halted. “How do you know about that, Ms. Stone?”

“Why did you tell me about Brennan, Agent Mercer?”

“Because I want the truth. I want to know what really happened in Georgetown and why. I want justice for the victims. It could be Hartman or someone else. I don’t care about probabilities; I want facts.”

Emily studied his face, noting his agitation. She was relieved when she felt that his emotions were genuine. “I want the truth too, Agent Mercer. Yes, I spoke to Joe after he escaped those operators… and you. He’s flawed but not a cold-blooded killer.”

“But you won’t tell me where he is, will you?”

Emily watched a goldfinch fly by. “Call me Emily. I believe you want the truth, but I can’t tell you where he is. I’ll buy him all the time he needs to find it—the truth.”

“Call me Alex or just Mercer. The pressure is high, Emily. This is bigger than the Georgetown killings. It’s about trust in the system. Hartman doesn’t have much time. I feel the investigation is already settled, and the grand finale is near.”

“You mean presenting a solution rather than justice?” Emily trembled with anger.

“I’m afraid so. Please persuade Joe to talk to me.”

30. Barn Door

As the sun faded, his face only lit by the open laptop, Joe Hartman stared at the screen, captivated by a potential backdoor in the AI chips powering countless devices. The implications of a hidden communications channel were staggering.

There were no traces of the data packets exchanged between the cars’ AIs, leaving Joe to ponder how many other devices were already communicating in the dark. It was as if Bolt had cunningly embedded this capability into the chips, evading detection.

Joe, not a hardware specialist, speculated that nanotechnology and novel materials facilitated this. Physics dictated a direct connection confined to a few meters, explaining the ripple effect from the cars' data. The first cars targeted Victim Zero, suggesting a deliberate initial signal.

Whoever attacked the young man willingly accepted the resulting casualties as collateral damage. Joe felt sick and had to admit that he totally believed Bolt was capable of such a move. “I should have stopped him when I had the chance,” he muttered, recalling Bolt’s time in his research group.

Joe stood up to turn on the lights but was startled to see movement on the dirt road leading to the wooden cabin.

He quickly switched the lights off again and grabbed the pump gun that David had left with him. Looking around for cover in panic, he decided to duck next to the stove in the cooking area, which was a few feet left of the door. He heard a car coming to a stop, and a door slammed shut.

As the cabin door opened, he aimed the gun over the stove, his heart pounding.

“Anybody home?” David Donnelly asked as he switched on the light in the dark cabin.

“Jeez, Dave!” Joe Hartman lowered the gun, sweat on his forehead.

"You seem jumpy. Thought the woods would calm you," David said, smiling.

"Not much chance to relax," Joe replied, weakly smiling back.

"Help me unload the truck, then we'll compare notes." David held up a six-pack of Samuel Adams Lager.

For the first time that day, Joe felt not totally lost anymore.

After setting up the antenna for his radio frequency tracker, David took two bottles of Sam Adams from the fridge.

Sitting at the wooden kitchen table with their bottles before them, Joe looked at David. “How’s Emily keeping up?”

“Pretty well, I must say. Tough young lady she is.”

“I’m sorry I dragged her into this,” Joe said, looking distant.

“It wasn’t your fault. What could you have done differently?”

“Many things, I’m afraid.”

“There’s truth,” David said while intently studying the label of his beer.

“Above all, I should have dealt with Jason Bolt when I had the chance.”

David perked up. “Why do you say this? You looked so downbeat when I arrived that I didn’t want to ask until we sat, but have you found anything?”

“Much more than I ever wanted to, actually. Dave, you won’t believe this, but it seems that Bolt builds a backdoor into the AI chips he produces. You remember we talked about swarming? Well, seems he’s done it.”

David was taken aback. “Walk me through it, Joe.”

Joe opened the laptop and explained how he found the backdoor.

After taking a long swig from his bottle, David looked his old friend in the eyes.

“This is fucking huge. This is no backdoor; this is a wide-open barn door. And all in the hands of a psychopath who just killed two dozen people as collateral damage.”

“And it sounds utterly crazy. I mean, if I go to the public with this, nobody will believe me, the mad scientist who is the primary subject himself.”

“Don’t get me wrong, Joe, but that would be the best-case scenario. The worst case is that they do believe you. It would cause outright panic and public unrest. Nothing can be trusted anymore. Hospitals, planes, banks, your phone, absolutely nothing.”

Both men sat together in silence for what seemed like an eternity.

“Do you think Bolt manipulated FBI’s SENTINEL to cover up his tracks?” David asked, his voice coarse.

“I’m not sure. It could be. It could be something entirely different. Remember I was at the initial briefing at the FBI? Maybe it was just this—wrong time and wrong place.”

“Or Jason found out you had the data and got worried you might steer the investigation toward him. He’s pretty much aware that you’re not his biggest fan,” David said, scratching his chin. “When the two FBI Agents were questioning me, they asked me specifically after your relationship with Bolt.

“But what really scares me is that both possible explanations would mean that there is much more going on at the FBI than an AI miscalculation.”

Joe solemnly nodded. “I never expected to become a conspiracy theorist. And now I feel like one of the main characters in the craziest of all.”

“I know it’s dicey, but we must talk to Emmy. Tell her how dangerous the situation is,” Joe pleaded with David.

“Yep, we need to do that, but not from here. I know a small brewery a few miles down the interstate. It’s always busy, and there are no cameras. Hank, the owner, is all about free speech and he’s got free public Wi-Fi, too.”

“I bet he doesn’t also offer free beer, does he?”

“That would indeed be too good to be true,” David laughed.

“So, how do you want to play this?”

“We take the laptop and set up a virtual private network that routes the data through enough hops around the world to make it hard to trace back. Then, we use the encrypted messenger app to make a voice call.”

Joe thought a moment about the setup. “How do we make sure the computer doesn’t send hidden data elsewhere? Just thinking of the backdoor.”

“Good point. The laptop has no AI chips on board, and we must be thorough with the firewall settings. The rest is praying to the Elders of the Internet.”

Joe shook his head but also had to smile. Finally, he shrugged and agreed to the plan.

Both men gathered the stuff they needed. Joe was grateful for the warm jacket David had brought for him as he stepped out into the chilly and dark night. Soon after both had settled into their seats, David’s truck’s engine started to rumble.

Only a minute after the truck’s backlights vanished into the dark, the radio scanner in the cabin started to beep urgently. But it remained unheard.

31. Research

After her meeting with Alex Mercer, Emily needed a moment alone. Despite the danger Brennan and his team posed, she decided to walk back to her hotel. Initially, she paused frequently, scanning her surroundings for any signs of pursuit. But soon, she calmed down, settling into a steady pace, her mind racing with the implications of Mercer's revelations. The scenic routes of Boston’s historic districts went unnoticed as her thoughts churned.

Suddenly, she halted. The memory of the car attacks in Georgetown surged back, flooding her with panic. What if somebody started turning self-driving cars into weapons? Had Georgetown been a brutal assassination?

She leaned against a nearby building, taking deep breaths. A middle-aged man approached, concern visible on his face. “Are you okay?” he asked.

Startled, Emily snapped, “I’m fine. Leave me alone!”

“Sorry... I’m sorry,” he muttered, shaking his head as he walked away.

Emily caught herself. “No, I’m sorry. That was kind of you,” she called after him.

“Rough day? It will pass,” he replied with a smile before continuing on his way.

Emily doubted it would pass. She noticed a sign for the T, indicating the subway station nearby. She had had enough of walking in the open. “How fitting,” she thought as she consulted her phone to navigate to her hotel by train.

Thirty minutes later, Emily sat at the small desk in her hotel room, her laptop open next to the little black notebook. She circled “Captain Luke Brennan” and “General Richard Clayton.”

Online searches for Brennan yielded nothing. She expected as much; any special operator worth their salt wouldn’t leave a digital footprint. Mercer, too, was a ghost online.

Frustrated, she opened the mini-fridge under the desk, grabbed a Coke, and took a few gulps, hoping the caffeine and sugar would help her focus. She paced the room before sliding back into the chair.

A search for Richard Clayton brought more results. The general was a decorated war hero known for leading from the front. His Marines affectionately called him “Ironhand,” a testament to his fierce reputation and leadership. He now commanded a combined task force of Marines and Rangers. Clayton seemed like someone not to be messed with. But why was Joe in his crosshairs?

Digging deeper, Emily found an obituary for Sarah Clayton, the general’s only child, killed in action a year ago. Sarah, a young Marine lieutenant, died during a rescue mission. There were also posts of Sarah with her father, showing Clayton as a caring dad.

Then Emily found a Reddit post about an autonomous drone incident killing a Marine squad in a blue-on-blue incident, supposedly covered up by the Department of Defense. The post was from a year ago, the same time Sarah died. The account was deleted, but Emily’s blood ran cold. Was this too much of a coincidence?

Emily took a deep breath and moved to the window, staring into the Boston night. The implications of her findings were chilling. Speculative as it was, it felt like a lead worth pursuing. She needed to discuss this with Joe and David.

Her phone chimed from the bed at that exact moment.

32. Going Public

Robert Weston was pacing through the Oval Office, his hands clasped behind his back.

“Mister President, there is only so much we can do,” said Jack McBride, the FBI director, sitting on one of the plush, cream-colored sofas. His tablet lay on the coffee table, a file opened on it.

Weston abruptly stopped in front of the Resolute Desk and turned to McBride.

“That’s hard to believe, Jack. You’re telling me that the FBI, the NSA, and everybody else is unable to find one single university professor? Aren’t we supposed to have something like complete surveillance after siphoning millions into hard- and software? Or is the man a ghost?”

McBride adjusted his silk Hermes tie. “I can assure you that he is very real. But he is not just any professor but one of the nation’s experts on artificial intelligence. If anybody knows how to trick our systems, it’s probably him. May I remind you that he single-handedly unleashed the cars in Georgetown on a killing spree?”

“I still don’t buy that, honestly,” Weston said, shaking his head.

“The question is probably another one,” McBride said cautiously.

“Please enlighten me, what is it then?”

“If the public buys it.”

McBride studied the floral patterns on the opposite wall and waited for a reaction.

Robert Weston deflated visibly and sat down on the other sofa, pondering the potential fallout if they failed.

“Yeah, I know. The polls show it. Social media analysis shows it: America wants an answer. And they need a government that delivers, Jack.”

“Mister President, that’s my whole point. They need a strong leader, and you are a strong leader. Let us go public with Hartman and show them how we deal with terrorists.”

Weston pondered his answer for a moment, then straightened his back.

“Okay, we go public. We go hunting. But I want a trial for Hartman. The man isn’t Osama Bin Laden. He’s an American citizen.”

“Who turned against us.”

“That’s the red line, Jack. It’s capture, not kill.” He hesitated a moment. “At least if it’s avoidable, Jack.”

McBride smiled thinly. “I can work with that, Mister President.”

After leaving the Oval Office, Jack McBride didn’t go straight to the J. Edgar Hoover Building but ordered his driver to take him to the Reflecting Pool. The Director’s Protective Detail agents knew that McBride liked to take a walk on the National Mall after meetings with POTUS, and although it was already turning dark, this wasn’t out of the ordinary.

McBride signaled his bodyguards to give him room for privacy, and they widened the formation around him, scanning the surroundings for threats.

He took a phone from his pocket, which wasn’t government-issued, although it looked exactly the same as his official one. It was equipped with top-tier encryption and designed to be untraceable.

He tapped an icon on the display and was connected right away.

“What did Bob say?”

“Good afternoon to you as well, Jason,” McBride answered, already annoyed by the speaker.

“Yeah, whatever. So, do we have a go?”

“Listen, Bolt, this is not how it works. POTUS wants to put Hartman on trial. But we will go public with his name and picture. And then it has to look like he went down in an attempt to arrest him.”

“Alrighty. As long as he goes with a blow…”

McBride clenched his jaw and silently counted to five.

“I would be grateful if you could take this matter more seriously. I don’t know about you, but I don’t want to have our country descend into anarchy and chaos.”

“Me as well, Jack, me as well. I know it’s also in my company’s best interest. That’s why I’m helping you guys, okay?”

“Jason, I really appreciate your help. Do you know where he is right now?”

“Yep, the last time our drones located him, he was hanging around in the woods in Maine. I’ll send you his coordinates, and you plan the show. But one more thing, those two agents you sent to me...”

“What about them?”

“The army guy, Mercer. Looks like he’s fraternizing with the enemy, so to speak. He’s been meeting Hartman’s ex-girlfriend a few hours ago. Did you know that?”

“No, but I’ll take care of this.”

After the call had ended, Jack McBride looked at the lights in the distance. Jason Bolt was a royal pain in the ass but a useful one, at least for now.

He waved at his protection detail to let them know he was finished. A few minutes later, McBride settled into the soft leather back seat of the armored car. The engine’s gentle hum did little to soothe his nerves. Lost in thought, he gazed out at the darkening city on his way back to his office.

35. Out of Reservation

Alex Mercer was sitting at a simple white desk in the FBI Boston Field Office, reviewing the case information on the Georgetown incident supplied by SENTINEL. The open-plan office was quiet at this time of day, which made it easier to concentrate. Mercer switched the user interface to expert mode to see the data and its relationships as SENTINEL analyzed and tagged them, not the simple chat mode that was the standard way to interact with the system. He always felt uneasy without seeing the underlying data, like the system was a black box.

He found it puzzling that Jason Bolt only appeared as a witness based on the transcript of the interview he had conducted with him earlier today but not related to his role as the main supplier of AI onboard chips, which surely were also to be found in most of the ‘killing cars’ that went rampage on M Street.

His phone vibrated and announced a text message that he read with a hint of a smile: “Meet me ASAP, E.” The location data for a hotel was attached, and he saw on the map application that it was a short drive there.

“Well, that was fast,” he said to himself as he typed a reply: “In 15.” After the picture of Joe Hartman went viral on all channels, he had expected a reaction from Emily Stone. He briefly considered calling his partner Jake Lin, who was spending the night with his family but refrained from doing so for this exact reason. If he was going to speak to the new public enemy number one off the record, he didn’t want to drag his friend into it.

He automatically checked the magazine of his Glock 17 service weapon and holstered it back as he went for the elevator. He might have been open to Hartman’s innocence, but he also firmly believed in being always prepared. And with Brennan’s team in the picture, the professor might not be the biggest threat.

Fifteen minutes later, he pulled over his black 1968 Ford Mustang in front of the address Emily Stone had sent him. He was grateful that his private car had no AI onboard, giving him much more freedom. Mercer believed the insurance premium for this perk was serious but worth every cent.

He found Emily standing in front of the building, gripping her backpack straps, her eyes shadowed with worry.

“I’m unsure if this is a huge mistake, Alex.”

“Me neither, Emily. I mean, being here obviously violates at least five department guidelines,” he answered with a weak smile.

He sensed her growing uneasiness and added, “Here’s the deal: we’ll be fine as long as Hartman, you, or Donnelly don’t cross me. I might have to take Hartman in for the public's safety … or his. But not until I hear his story. I'll treat him as innocent until proven guilty, alright?”

He held out his hand, and after a moment of hesitation, Emily shook it.

“You need to leave your phone here. I will do the same. We can’t be tracked to Joe’s location.”

Now, Mercer hesitated a moment, but finally, he agreed, and they both went inside to hand over the phones to the concierge to keep them safe.

Mercer and Emily drove in silence on Interstate 95. After briefly discussing Emily’s findings on General Clayton and his daughter Sarah, they agreed that it was Joe’s turn to explain what he had discovered to Alex.

Lost in thought, they watched the trees blur past. Mercer checked the mirrors constantly, wary of any tail in the darkness. He had also stopped a couple of times in resting areas to lose any tail, but there weren’t any guarantees he had been successful.

Finally, after consulting her black notebook, then directed Mercer off the Interstate onto smaller, more isolated roads leading to David’s cabin.

“This is it, then. After half a mile, we should see David’s cabin,” Emily said and looked to Mercer.

“Well, that’s as remote as it comes,” he bent forward to get a better look at the dense canopy of trees. He slowly drove on, uncertain of what to expect at the end of the road.

“I can see lights down the road,” David said from the window where he had been standing for the last hour keeping watch.

Joe looked up from his laptop, where he’d been vainly searching the memory pack for traces of the swarming technology. He was acutely aware that his theory was intriguing for people with a background in artificial intelligence but probably not very convincing for an FBI agent who would want to see some cold, hard proof.

At first, he had been sulking on the way from the tavern where David and Emily had basically decided about his fate. But then again, any plan was better than doing nothing. After he regained control over his emotions, he agreed with his friends’ analysis; his best chance to stay alive was to convince Mercer that something much bigger was at play.

“They’ve pulled over, and the lights inside the car are on. I can see Emily and the Fed, Mercer,” David reported, holding his field glasses.

“Alright, let’s do this,” Joe muttered under his breath and gave David a thumbs up.

Slowly, David opened the door, showing his empty hands, field glasses dangling around his neck.

Mercer opened the door of his Mustang and got out, mirroring David’s gesture, while Emily emerged from the passenger seat.

“Welcome to the woods,” David said and forced a smile, beckoning the two to come inside.

Joe waited anxiously for them to enter the cabin, his forehead covered with beads of sweat and his heart racing so loud in his ears he couldn’t even hear Emily’s and Mercer’s steps.

Meanwhile, in Boston, Mercer’s and Jake Lin’s phones chimed at the same time. It was a notification from PHOENIX, the FBI’s internal platform for background investigations, physical access, and security clearances.

Jake rose from the family table, his face blanching as he read: “Status Update: You are temporarily suspended pending an FBI Security Division (SecD) investigation. Surrender your badge and service weapon immediately. All FBI facilities and systems access are terminated. Refrain from discussing this matter with anyone outside the official channels. Await further communication from SecD.”

38. Revelations

“It’s time to go,” David said with a firm voice. On the other side of the lake, the flashing red and blue lights of the Beavercreek sheriff’s and firefighters’ cars could be seen now. “We have about three minutes now.”

He retrieved an Eberlestock Renegade backpack, and another Remington pump gun from the manhole.

Joe’s eyes widened as David took military-issue smart glasses from the bag and put them on. “No worries, they are on passive mode, using GPS data, improved night vision, and some advanced object detection.”

Then he took out a poncho with the same camouflage pattern as the ruck and held it to Emily, who stood there in her white, although now dirty, T-shirt and beige pants. “Take this. Let’s get moving. I take the point, Joe, you’re at the rear.”

As they walked away into the woods at a cautious pace, Joe reflected on the last minutes. As far as Murphy’s law went, he didn’t dare to hope the worst was behind them. He looked around. The forest was dense now, and he would have been lost without David’s guidance. The trees and shrubs provided shelter and hid the unknown lurking in the dark.

Emily turned around and smiled nervously at Joe, her breath forming small clouds in the chilly air. Joe smiled back and nodded at her in a way he hoped to look confidently. But he was just barely able to hide his growing unease. His friend David seemed to be a different person since the drone attack.

“What are we going to do next?” Emily asked softly.

“Find a place to hide again. Then, find out what the situation is with Mercer. We need his support to stop Bolt,” Joe said and shrugged.

David stopped, removed, and opened his backpack. He took out three small plastic bottles. “Ketones. Taste like robot piss,” he said and looked at Emily. “Pardon my French, but they will keep us going for the next hours.”

Emily wrinkled her nose. “Are those safe?”

David took his bottle and downed it in one gulp. “It’s what your body produces when you’re starving, minus the starvation.”

Reluctantly, Joe took a swig and grimaced.

When Alex Mercer regained consciousness, his splitting headache was fueled by a low rumbling sound. His mind felt foggy, and he struggled to piece together where he was. He tried to open his eyes, the dim light stabbing at his vision, and squinted, disoriented. The last thing he remembered was being in the cabin, the explosion, then darkness. Where was he now? His stomach lurched at a sudden downward movement, making him aware that he was moving—no, flying.

He forced his eyes open again, the blurry shapes around him slowly coming into focus. His head pounded with each heartbeat, and he fought against the nausea rising in his throat. The face of the man who had ambushed him came into view, strapped in a harness, smiling in a way that made Mercer’s blood boil.

Mercer tried to get up, but a sharp pain shot through his side, and he realized he was restrained in his seat. Panic mixed with anger as he pulled against the restraints.

“Easy there, Sir,” the man sitting next to his assailant said, his voice annoyingly calm, “we’re airborne, so there’s no way to leave unless you jump.”

Mercer’s memory began to return in flashes—the cabin, the explosion, trying to save Brennan. “You son of a bitch,” he managed to say through gritted teeth, “just wait until I’m able to return the favor.”

“Sorry, Major, I didn’t recognize you. Was a bit of a tense situation.”

Mercer looked around, trying to gather his bearings. He was in an e-chopper. Luke Brennan was strapped on a gurney, wrapped in a thermal blanket, and having an IV dangle from the ceiling, but he was awake.

“He’ll live. Hanson wasn’t so lucky,” the man facing him said.

“Where are you taking me?”

“Back to base, Major.”

“What’s that with all the Major shit? Who are you?”

“Sergeant Mendez, Sir, and this is Lance Corporal Decker.”

“Alright, and I’m Mercer. Or Agent Mercer. But not Major. Not anymore.”

“Well, technically, not Agent anymore, either,” Brennan said, turning his face to him. “And thanks for taking care of my leg, Mercer,” he added, turning his face to the ceiling again.

“Whoa, wait. What was that with not being an Agent anymore?” Mercer said, his headache getting even worse.

“As far as we know, the FBI suspended you,” Mendez said, pointing to the tablet on his lap as if that would explain anything.

“Maybe you should try to rest for the next few minutes, Sir. General Clayton is expecting you for a debriefing, Major.”

Mercer closed his eyes and decided to let it slip.

After marching through the forest for about 60 minutes without exchanging a word, David Donnelly signaled them to halt again. They had arrived at a creek that gurgled through a bend, followed by a small eddy. David crouched down and drank from the water, motioning Joe and Emily to do the same. He also produced two soft flasks from his backpack and filled them.

“How did they find us?” Joe asked while chewing on an energy bar that David had handed to both of them.

“My best guess is that they followed Mercer and Emmy to the cabin,” David answered thoughtfully.

“You think he betrayed us?” Emily asked wearily.

“We can’t rule it out,” Joe said while raising a brow and looking at Emily.

“No, we can’t rule it out. But that would have been a suicide mission, given the amount of C4 that blew us up. Somebody wanted to make very sure, that we were very dead indeed,” David said with a small shrug.

“Maybe he had a tail and didn’t notice. Was there anything suspicious on your ride?” Joe asked Emily.

“We left our phones in my hotel in Boston. Alex was making an effort that we weren’t followed when he drove.”

“In your hotel? Didn’t know you were that close now with ‘Alex’?” Joe scowled, making air quotes when mentioning Mercer’s first name.

“You jealous now, Joe? Didn’t know you cared anyways,” Emily scowled back.

“Alright, kids, that’s not helpful,” David interrupted them. “When this is over, you two can take a long walk in the park and sort things out. But until then, focus!”

An uneasy silence lingered for a minute until David spoke again. “So, back to the drone raid. It was a bit flashy, so the question is, who was behind it, and why the fireworks?”

“Maybe it was some kind of public relations stunt. Show the world that Joe is scattered all through the woods of Maine,” Emily frowned.

“That would make quite a story. Maybe making it look like you blew yourself up while building a bomb or a killer drone,” David reasoned.

“Well, having explosives and weapons hidden somewhere seems to be more your style, to be honest,” Joe said while watching David carefully.

“Fair enough,” David shrugged and put on his backpack again, “but I also know how to handle them.”

“Maybe it was just Bolt being Bolt,” Emily said, trying to defuse the situation.

“Yeah, that fucker,” Joe admitted, and David nodded.

“We’ll find out more when we access the news feeds. Let’s get moving again, guys,” David said and turned around.

“Major Mercer, come in,” General Richard Clayton said, sitting in his combat uniform behind a nondescript desk at the Marine Corps headquarters at Henderson Hall.

Alex Mercer entered the room briskly and came not quite to attention before he answered. “Good to see you, General, although the circumstances are less desirable. And with all due respect, it’s Agent nowadays.”

“And that’s a shame, especially since the FBI seems to be reconsidering your relationship with each other. But enough chitchat. Have a seat, Alex.”

“Thank you, Sir. I understand we are here to talk about Joe Hartman?”

“Amongst other things. But first I would indeed appreciate your opinion on Hartman.”

“Permission to speak freely?” The General nodded.

“He’s a dick, but probably not a killer.” Mercer paused. “Before someone tried to bust his balls with a lot of C4, he and his friends, Emily Stone and David Donnelly, told me a rather wild story. Although, if true, we’re at the brink of anarchy and chaos.”

“How come?”

“He explained that nobody less than Jason Bolt added a hidden backdoor to the AI chips that his company produces. You could stealthily manipulate every device running on it. And that is a lot. Basically, everything, from hospitals to banks to cars.”

Richard Clayton closed his eyes and rubbed his forehead, an unusual gesture of stress for the battle-hardened warrior facing him, as far as Mercer could tell.

“Go ahead,” Clayton said under his breath.

“Well, it seems that the killing cars in Georgetown were the first demonstration of this capability. Hartman worked out that it was likely an assassination, and other casualties were just for covering up the fact.

“So, General, I’ve shown you mine. What about you show me yours? Why was Brennan and his team after Hartman? I nearly shot Luke when they tried to kidnap the professor.”

“The first man that was killed in Georgetown was a whistleblower. He contacted me anonymously and offered information about the autonomous drone program. Captain Monroe was about to meet him. I hoped…” Clayton stopped in his tracks.

Mercer nodded. “You hoped that he had something about Sarah.”

Clayton looked him straight in the eyes while he was searching for words. “Yes. We both know that death is part of the soldier’s life. When Sarah enlisted in the Marines, it was clear that this could happen, being killed in action. But this… I need to know what happened.”

Alex pondered the situation and decided. “I can’t imagine how you must be feeling. She was…” Mercer wasn’t sure how to continue. “We also discussed this…“

“You spoke about Sarah?!” The general leaned forward abruptly, moving to the edge of his chair.

“Yes, they tried to understand your interest in Hartman, and Stone did her research. Hartman told me Bolt likely used a buggy version of the onboard AI. It wouldn’t have been the first time Bolt used this approach to train an AI in the wild. Unfortunately, this sounds realistic enough.”

Richard Clayton stood up and walked to the window, straightening his cammies. His eyes wandered over the lawn in front of the building and rested briefly on the Stars and Stripes flying from the white flag pole.

“The Autonomous Drone Continuity Program is about to be set into action. Tomorrow at 2400 hours. You know what that means? The Russians or Chinese hit us hard? Our drones retaliate. No human interaction required. Their AIs select the targets. They can even lock us out if they believe we are compromised. Flying killer robots on autopilot, deciding who lives and who dies. They have their independent nuclear power stations and their own warheads stored across the country. Small drone bases hidden in the U.S. and abroad. And guess who built them? Bolt Industries. We’re handing this motherfucker enough firepower to not only start a civil war but wreak havoc around the globe.”

Clayton turned around to Mercer, whose jaw went slack. “And nobody wants to hear about it. God knows I’ve tried to make them listen. But the Secretary of Defense and POTUS think I’m just an old fart standing in the way of progress. We need to stop this. We need to stop Bolt.”

“Affirmative, Sir,” Alex said, his mind racing through the potential scenarios. “But no matter how I think about it, we will need Joe Hartman for this.”

41. Missions

“What can I do for you, Sir?” Helen Koop looked tensely at her tablet, still processing that the Attorney General had asked for a private conversation. William Banks was smiling at her. The former Governor of Arizona was still under forty and handsome, with a sharp intellect, and well-connected in his party. The stuff future presidents were made of, Helen thought, which added to her unease.

“Thank you for your time, Helen. I imagine you are pretty tied up with the Hartman case, so let’s get to the point. I understand you know Hartman personally?”

“Well, we’ve met on a few occasions. He’s one of the leading experts on complex systems. I mean, he was…”

“And that’s why you asked him to your initial briefing on the Georgetown massacre,” Banks said as a statement rather than a question.

Koop answered anyway. “Of course, if I had known what I knew today, I wouldn’t have brought him into the meeting.”

“But then again, SENTINEL wouldn’t have identified him so quickly, so I suppose we have to thank you.”

“If you put it this way,” Helen said, wary of where this was going.

“Still, I wonder if you believe Hartman was truly capable of committing such a crime, apart from SENTINEL.”

“To be honest, a lot of us were surprised. But then again, it makes sense, although I still have questions.”

“So do I, Assistant Director. I would find it unfortunate if this were going in the wrong direction, and the people responsible would get away with this atrocity.” He paused and leaned in, looking sternly at her.

Helen felt a chill. “I assure you I will do whatever it takes to hold them accountable. Do you think Hartman had help?”

“Easy, Helen. I don’t know what to think,” Banks smiled warmly at her. “But I noted some strange coincidences here and there. Decisions that could have been nudged. It’s like somebody is pulling strings. But I can’t see the bigger picture, which disturbs me.”

Helen Koop nodded. “I understand that sentiment, Sir.”

“Okay, I don’t want to keep you. Look, I just sent you my personal contact details. If you come across anything you think I should know, don’t hesitate to use them,” he said and held his phone into the camera.

After the call had ended, Helen Koop rubbed her eyes. Whatever Bank’s motives were, a direct line to the Attorney General could be useful. But she had to tread carefully as this had just become a completely different kind of power game.

“Clear my calendar for the next forty-eight hours, Vesta,” Rebecca Hayes instructed her virtual assistant, shuffling papers on her university desk.

“You have an appointment with the Dean tomorrow at 09:00 AM. Shall I cancel it?” Vesta asked in a pleasant tone.

“Nothing’s going to keep me,” she muttered, glancing at the stack of printouts.

“I’m sorry, but I didn’t understand your last instruction.”

Rebecca sighed, feeling a twinge of frustration. “Adjourn the meeting with Dean Rodriguez to his earliest convenience. I’m taking two days off to get my daughter home.”

As Vesta confirmed the adjustments, Rebecca's thoughts drifted to Maria. Her daughter needed her help after Georgetown. Nothing was more important now.

“If I should ever get my hands on that fucker responsible for Georgetown, I’m going to make him pay.”

“The person responsible for the Georgetown massacre is Professor Joseph Hartman,” Vesta chirped helpfully.

“That’s the one,” Rebecca Hayes snarled, her brows tightly knit.

42. Linking up

After leaving the FBI building, Jake Lin needed coffee and a hearty breakfast. After a short walk, he entered one of his favorites, “The Anvil.” He looked up at the ceiling, which featured a mix of wood panels and glossy white tiles, reflecting the soft, warm lighting from the overhead globe-shaped chandeliers. The walls were adorned with white subway tiles, and large, darkly framed windows lined one side of the restaurant.

Jake got seated at one of the dark wooden tables, still thinking about his friend and partner. Absentmindedly, he opened the menu and wondered what had happened to Alex in the last twelve hours. The video footage of the burnt-down cabin in Maine where Joe Hartman supposedly died in an attempt to prepare explosives for another attack made him more suspicious than ever. Why would an alleged mastermind that manipulated AIs easily to transform autonomous cars into killing machines need to tinker with a few kilograms of C4? And where did he get it in the first place? This all didn’t add up in his professional opinion. But it made a hell of a story on social media, as he noticed when overhearing a man on the next table recording a video of himself musing about the dramatic end of the murderous professor from Boston. People were so easily played. But in a few hours, maybe days, when the forensics were finished, it would become clear what happened in Maine — or not.

When he looked up from the selection of breakfasts, his unconsciousness caught something on the edge of his vision outside on the street. He wasn’t sure what it was, but his heart started beating faster. Following his instincts, he dropped the menu and jumped on his feet.

When the coffee was ready, Joe Hartman grabbed two mugs and went outside to the small clearing where David Donnelly had prepared the small StarConnect device to allow them to go online. He found David sitting in the shadow of a tree, leaning at its trunk, his eyes closed.

“Thanks for the coffee, man,” David said without opening them.

“How did you know it was me?” Joe asked and lowered himself next to him.

“When you trust all your senses, you get much more information than what the eyes see,” David answered, gratefully accepting the coffee.

“You seem to be a man of many talents, Dave. I must say, I’m a bit surprised.”

“Yeah, I noticed. Things are not always what they seem, which is even more true for people. But I’m your friend, Joe, and you need to trust me. Our history made us who we are today, and I’m no different. When this is all over, I’ll try to answer all your questions, but now we need to focus. Today isn’t about absolute truths, if those even exist, but surviving. You need to trust me, Joe. Can you do this?”

Joe thought about the years he had been friends with David. Not once had he been disappointed by him. Maybe it was about time to trust his feelings. His eyes went to the cabin, where Emily stood in the doorframe with her coffee, waving at him guardedly when their eyes met.

“Yes. Yes, I can do this, Dave,” Joe said, still looking at Emily. David, who had been watching him, smiled.

The indicator, blinking red for the last twenty minutes, suddenly switched to green, signaling that StarConnect had uplinked with one of the satellites above them.

“Here we go,” David said, putting his smart glasses back on.

A few patrons looked up from their devices as Jake Lin scrambled out of the restaurant. Scanning the street left and right, the steady flow of pedestrians made it harder to spot what had alerted him.

A few paces away, he noticed a man looking into a store window, having something vaguely familiar about him. Once Jake moved in his direction, the man briskly walked away and turned right into a small alley. Jake quickly checked his Glock 17 in his holster and followed the man, trying not to attract too much attention from cameras and their crowd control algorithms. When he entered the shaded alley, he noticed that there wasn’t any surveillance—a good spot for any business that should remain undetected then. The man he had followed here slowly turned around.

“Whoa, what happened to your face?” Jake asked, surprised.

“You should see the other guy,” Alex Mercer answered with a lopsided grin, his face still swollen and bruised in a dark purple where the carbine’s buttstock had connected with his temple.

Both men shook hands. “I thought I had a shitty night, but yours looks worse. What’s the gist?”

As Mercer summarized the events since they last spoke, Jake constantly shook his head.

“This is the craziest shit I’ve ever heard, Alex!”

“Affirmative. Totally fucked up. So how about you?”

“Uhh, a walk in the park, actually. We got suspended last night, my wife threatened to divorce me, and a few hours ago, I was called in by Koop and reinstated. But I feel this was on purpose, just using me to get to you… Shit,” Jake said and looked around the still lonely and calm alley.

“No worries, that was to be expected. And it’s a good thing that you’re back in the game. Listen, there’s something I need you to do.”

David Donnelly was scrolling through the feeds on his smart glasses with a quick gesture of his right hand while Joe Hartman and Emily Stone stood beside him a few meters away from the StarConnect device.

“So, it looks like you’re dead, Joe,” David said, and Joe frowned.

“Social media and news outlets have it that you blew yourself up while cobbling together a killer drone with a few pounds of plastic explosives,” David explained.

“But isn’t that a good thing if they believe Joe is dead?” Emily asked.

“Only as long as nobody wants to make sure, he stays that way,” David replied, looking directly at her.

“This is a red herring, I agree,” Joe said thoughtfully, scratching the stubble on his chin. “It fits into Bolt’s scheme of paving the way for his greater plan, whatever it is. I’m dead; the case is solved. It would be pretty unfortunate if I turned up somewhere and claimed otherwise.

“It’s a thin story as well; this only holds as long as there is no thorough forensic investigation of the cabin.”

“Well, it looks like the drones had some Thermite in the mix for good measure. It burns hot enough to melt through anything. Classic overkill if you want no traces left behind.” David said, looking sickly pale.

“That’s the handwriting of Bolt if you ask me,” Joe said.

“And if you ask me, there are too many people running around trying to kill you and, by extension, us,” Emily stepped up to him.

“We must take our chances and make a strong ally to stop this. Any information about Mercer?” She looked at David.

“Nothing in the public feeds, but honestly, he’s just one rogue FBI agent. That won’t be enough, even if he got out of Beavercreek alive.”

Joe swallowed. “There’s only one logical conclusion.”

“Care to expand?” David asked, taking off his smart glasses.

“Someone with the means and the motive to stop Bolt,” Joe said, unsure if he liked where his own reasoning was going.

“The General. Clayton,” Emily completed his thought.

David looked at some distant point for a moment and cleared his throat. “I’m afraid you’re right.”

“But how do we get to him?” Emily asked wearily.

“We’ll call in the cavalry,” David answered and put the smart glasses back on.

43. The Bucket Ends

Captain Steve Monroe leaped from the Bell UH-1Y Venom, which had just touched down on an intersection of two logging roads a mile from McKenzie’s cabin. The precision landing without AI assistance was a challenge for their pilot, which he had gladly accepted. Most senior pilots preferred the good old direct action over the more video game-like experience anyway, even without the threat of a backdoor.

Four marines with M4 carbines secured the chopper’s perimeter. Monroe walked to the meeting point David Donnelly had suggested. The encrypted message from Donnelly, attached to an unsuspicious email, was unexpected. Hartman was willing to meet with Clayton, and he made it urgent. Given Hartman’s first encounter with Brennan’s team, Monroe had assumed more persuasion would be needed.

He waited a few minutes until he saw movement nearby. He had been watched until the group decided to proceed. He recognized Joe Hartman, David Donnelly, and Emily Stone from the pictures in their files. Donnelly looked confident and focused, Hartman wearily, and Stone tried to hide a grimace with every step she took.

Monroe extended his hand. “Captain Steven Monroe, U.S. Marine Corps. I’m General Clayton’s aide.”

Donnelly was the first to take it. “David Donnelly.” His handshake was firm and energetic.

Emily was the next. “I’m Emily Stone.”

“Pleased to meet you, ma’am,” Monroe said automatically, but he immediately regretted it when he realized the young woman’s recent ordeal.

“Joe Hartman, but I guess you already knew that. You haven’t been with the thugs that tried to kidnap me,” Joe Hartman stepped forward and looked the clean-shaven officer up and down. “No offense.”

“None taken, Sir. I understand that time is of the essence, and our ride is waiting. So is the General. Please follow me,” he answered, motioning for the Super Huey, idling a hundred meters down the logging road.

As they walked, Joe considered the possibility of delivering himself to his torturers. Images of waterboarding flashed through his mind. He shivered, suppressing despair. This decision could either save them or lead to doom.

Jake Lin seriously doubted his life choices as he entered the evidence room. When Alex Mercer asked him for help, he didn’t expect misappropriation of evidence in a murder case. If this wasn’t the most significant domestic threat in U.S. history, he was sure he would lose his badge for good, including his pension and any chance to work in law enforcement for the rest of his life. Even a shopping mall cop would be out of the question then.

He held his badge next to the reader at the checkout terminal. The cold air of the evidence room prickled Jake Lin's skin, making the hairs on his neck stand on end. He looked straight into the facial recognition unit that, with a combination of cameras and lidar scanners, ensured he was the person his badge claimed to be.

“Welcome, Agent Jacob Lin. This transaction’s ID is A3B7X9Z1 and will be recorded. What items do you wish to check out?” the synthetic voice of the terminal asked.

Jake stated the case number and asked for Gideon Herzog’s personal belongings, which included a smartwatch, a broken tablet, a wallet, and a memory pack. All electronic devices had been booked as dysfunctional because the EMP had destroyed their chips.

For a moment, he expected that his request would be denied or security would storm into the room to arrest him, but neither happened.

Instead, he saw the robotic arm behind the storage room’s thick, bulletproof glass window whirl into action, retrieving Jake’s requested items, each neatly sealed into an evidence bag with an RFID label.

After his digital signature was on the terminal, the bags slid out and were collected in a plastic box he took.

The elevator’s doors closed behind Lin, and he looked into its large mirror. He had sweat beads on his forehead—and this was still the easy part. Now, he would have to smuggle the box’s contents out of the building. He left the elevator on the floor where he had booked a desk for the day and sat down when he had found his place, the box on the floor next to him.

He took out a burner phone and opened an app marketed as ‘purely educational’. Using the phone's NFC chip, the app read the RFID tags on the evidence bags and cloned them. Essentially, the device would now fool any scanner into believing the tags were still present by responding with a copy of the labels' IDs.

He took the tablet and the memory pack out of the box and looked around. The shared office was empty except for a pair of agents at the other end of the room. The security cameras in the corners covered all workstations, so he had to act as unconscious as possible. He bowed down and slipped the devices into a daypack he had brought next to the box and the burner phone under the left evidence bags. Hoping the desk had covered his sleight of hand, he closed the daypack lined with a metal mesh that should the original RFID signals. Otherwise, he noted, he was royally fucked.

He stood up and carried the box to the evidence lockers at the wall. He closed it and locked the door, holding his badge to the reader and looking into the small camera. The locker registered the cloned RFID labels, and the system logged that Agent Lin had securely stored away the evidence he had checked out twenty minutes earlier.

As the elevator doors closed behind him, Jake Lin felt a momentary relief, quickly replaced by the tension of what lay ahead. Twenty minutes later, he was sitting on a bench in John Marshall Park, shaded by a large tree, his daypack on the ground next to him.

A young, broad-shouldered man approached the bench from the other side and sat down, slinging down a daypack that looked exactly like his. After briefly studying the statue in the park’s center through his smart glasses, he grabbed Lin’s daypack and strolled away.

Jake thought it was a bit ironic that, in the digital age, this was such a classic move that left fewer traces if done right. Escaping AI-based surveillance still required very traditional tradecraft.

“Spartan Actual, Spartan Two, handover completed; RTB,” Sergeant Enrique Mendez spoke softly without looking back.

As General Richard Clayton entered the small, windowless conference room in Henderson Hall, Lance Corporal Marty Decker snapped to attention. Alex Mercer had to suppress the same impulse, hardwired over years of service. Captain Steven Monroe, who had just barely straightened up, looked at Mercer with a hinted smile.

“As you were. The elusive Doctor Hartman,” Clayton nodded at Joe Hartman and extended his hand, which Joe shook after a short moment of hesitation.

“Doctor Donnelly, Miss Stone,” the General welcomed the rest of the small group. They had been given time to clean up and got a hearty breakfast from the chow hall. They stood in borrowed PTs and only David looked comfortable in the Marine green physical training uniform. Clayton gestured for them to sit around the light grey conference table with a cluster of chilled water bottles at its center.

“Before we get to the most pressing issues, I want to clarify something. I owe you an apology, professor. Based on yesterday’s information, the situation seemed to warrant sending a team after you. But I can see now that this was… ill-advised,” Clayton addressed Joe.

“Well, at least you didn't try to shred and roast me and my friends, so we’re good,” Joe said with a dismissive gesture, caught off guard by the General’s opening.

Clayton nodded curtly and continued.

“Let’s put all the cards on the table. Captain Monroe and Agent Mercer will brief you in more detail afterward, but we’re facing the biggest threat to the U.S. in its history. We have reason to believe that we face a conspiracy up to the highest echelons of government orchestrated by Jason Bolt. The last missing piece in the puzzle was that Bolt had compromised his AI chips with a backdoor. The Autonomous Drone Continuity Program will be launched in less than fourteen hours. It means that a completely autonomous drone force will be activated that can make its kill decisions on its own. And they can’t be stopped by human intervention. In theory, it is the perfect deterrent. But since the drones are operating with Bolt’s chips, this will give the man weapons capable of mass destruction. We’re facing a coup with us and our allies at gunpoint, no less.” Clayton paused and looked around. The shock on the weary faces of Joe, David, and Emily was clearly visible, even after all they had been through.

“That’s what the fucker was waiting for,” David was the first to find his voice again, shaking his head vigorously.

“Why is nobody stopping it?” Emily asked incredulously.

“President Weston was elected on the promise that domestic AI guarantees America’s superiority in the 21st century. Can you imagine what it would mean for him to admit that this AI wasn’t safe? And Bolt has done a thorough job,” Richard Clayton added, looking at Alex Mercer. “We believe the FBI is compromised. Other agencies and the Department of Defense likely as well.”

“Nobody is going to help us then,” Joe said, the resignation in his voice obvious.

“No, we need to help ourselves. The bucket ends here,” General Clayton pounded the table with his fist for emphasis.

In the now quiet room, Joe felt the gravity of the words sinking in.